>> Okay? Big money pours
into Wisconsin for the
midterms with a big
financial edge for
conservatives. Who's behind
the push and what are the
candidates saying about
issues ranging from gas
prices to corruption? This
is inside Wisconsin
politics.
politics. I'm Shawn Johnson
here with my colleagues,
Anya van Wagtendonk Zac
Schultz and Rich Kremer in
Eau Claire. Hey, everyone.
>> Hello.
>> So we have a lot of
issues to discuss today,
but I think we need to
start right off the top
with this big financial
push from conservatives and
specifically one
conservative group, which
is dumping a lot of money
into Wisconsin all at once.
Rich, you covered this
group. They are pretty much
brand new and already there
are huge spender. Tell us
about who they are and what
they're doing here.
>> By my math, they're the
biggest spender so far in
2026. So who they are?
They're called First
Amendment LLC. It is an
express advocacy group, so
it's not affiliated with
any specific candidate,
etc. or campaign. But it is
obviously a conservative
group because all the money
that they're putting into
Wisconsin is going against
Democrats, and it's a lot
of money, too. We're
talking about this group
was created last week, and
on the same day it reported
spending around $13 million.
And that's divided up by $9
million, going against
David Crowley in the race
for governor and the
remaining 3.4 million or so
going into key Assembly and
Senate races, as
Republicans and Democrats
vie for control of the
state legislature. And this
money, we don't know much
about what it's going to be
used for. But in the filing
it said it will be for
direct mail campaign
literature, phone calls,
digital ads, that sort of
thing. But it's hard to
tell where the money is
coming from, who this group
is. It appears to be
affiliated with a different
Virginia based PAC called
Make Liberty Win, and Fox
News did an article not
long ago about a tech
investor essentially
putting $40 million into
Make Liberty Win. I wasn't
able to see in the federal
campaign finance reports
whether that money was
transferred over, but it
appears that this new group
is flush with cash.
>> Okay. And so this comes
into an environment where
we already knew who some of
the big donors were in
Wisconsin, because they do
report their contributions.
And Republicans had a
pretty big advantage there,
too, did they not?
>> They did. Yeah. And just
just the top spenders this
year. I mean, it is the
First Amendment LLC group.
And then it's the
Republican Party of
Wisconsin. Those are the
two top spenders. And if
you look back to 2022, the
last race for governor, it
was Tony Evers was the
number one spender in state
politics. And the second
place runner up was the
Democratic Party of
Wisconsin. So we're seeing
a little bit of a flip of
those two parties in terms
of the money that they're
bringing in and spending.
>> And when it comes to
who's giving to the parties,
you have big contributions
from billionaires Diane
Hendricks and the U. Lines,
Richard Uihlein also has
his own group that's
running ads to help Tom
Tiffany Ana. This is a bit
of a switch, a flip, as we
rich mentioned there, in
terms of what we've gotten
used to in Wisconsin, where
Democrats seem to know how
to use this state law that
lets unlimited money flow
around from parties to
candidates.
>> Right? So you mentioned
those mega donors who have
essentially put tons of
money into the Republican
Party of Wisconsin, and
that's using a kind of
loophole in campaign
finance law that says that
there's a cap on how much
individuals can donate to
campaigns. There is not a
cap on what you can give to
parties, and then what
parties can spend. And so
this was a law that was
passed by Republicans, but
then Democrats ended up
using to kind of great
effect over many years. But
so I think there's a couple
of different reasons for
that, potentially. So one
reason is just like a very
kind of local reason, which
is that the former chair of
the Democratic Party, Ben
Wikler, is just known for
his kind of fundraising
prowess. And he has a sort
of national profile among
national Democrats. He's
very well respected among
sort of D.C. Democratic
circles. So he was really
the person. It wasn't like
the Democratic Party
immediately took advantage
of this law. It was when he
came into leadership in the
Democratic Party that
Democrats really kind of
took this and ran with it.
So it's possible, now that
he's no longer in
leadership, that that has
had some effect on the
state party's ability to
fundraise. I think another
thing also that's going on
here, though, is that even
though the governor's race
is going to be very tight
and is very important, and
even, you know, sort of
national politicos
recognize that the
Wisconsin governor's race
is important. Democrats are
also trying to flip
Congress. And so, you know,
I went and looked at a
number of the kind of big
Democratic mega donors who
often try to put money in
Wisconsin state elections,
and they're still spending
money this year, but
they're spending it on
congressional races in
other states. So we're
seeing much less of their
money come through the
Democratic Party. And
that's why I think, you
know, the combination of
huge spending from
Republicans and then some
amount of kind of taking
their foot off the gas from
Democrats shows that big
split.
>> Zac, you know, I kind of
got a theory in politics
that when you see these big
donors put a lot of money
into a race like ours, like
the race for governor, they
feel like they have a
chance at getting something
that they want, right? That
they they feel like they
have a chance of winning. I
mean, is it fair to, to say
that Republicans are
looking at Wisconsin is
maybe friendly ground in an
unfriendly environment?
>> It's interesting because
you have to look at both
the national environment
and the state environment
to realize there is a
difference in what we're
seeing out of the Midwest
and Northern American races
in Minnesota, tightening up
Wisconsin is always tight.
Michigan Senate, the
polling out of Maine Senate
being a lot tighter, which
is the opposite of what
we're hearing out of the
South, which is, you know,
Texas Democrats doing well
in Kansas, Senate race
being competitive and these
things that we really
hadn't heard of and kind of
expanding of what Arnie was
talking about. The map is
so large that these
Democratic national donors
are being pulled in a lot
of different directions.
Whereas in the past, Ben
Wikler could say, hey,
support Tony Evers to
protect Wisconsin's
electoral votes in the
presidential election,
protect the Assembly so
that Tony Evers veto still
matters when it comes to
drawing these maps. Invest
in our our Supreme Court
races so we can redraw
these maps and declare what
gerrymandering is. That
argument has already been
won. And so every investor
needs a new argument of why
they need to invest. And it
may be that some of them
are just looking in
different directions and
getting maybe greedy from a
Democratic point of view of,
hey, where else can we win?
Forgetting that Wisconsin
still competitive, this
race will be closer than
some of those other races
where they are investing
millions and neglecting the
Democrats here. And I think
you also have to look at
what does it matter for the
Assembly? Because if we're
talking about the state
Senate being more likely to
flip to Democrats because
they only need to win a
couple seats, and one of
them looks pretty solid,
and they've got a couple
good battleground options.
And if they think they're
going to lose the
Democratic race for
governor because they have
this national wave
overtaking Tom Tiffany's
ability to compete there,
backstop is the assembly
where they're very
localized races. They only
have to win a handful of
these seats to stop the
Democrats from doing
anything they want in the
next session if they hold
the Assembly. So that's
worth pouring all these
millions into. And that's
originally where these
billionaires were dumping
their money was into the
Republican Assembly. PACs
and all their money. So
it's they're also expanding
their own map as they're
saying, hey, maybe, maybe
Tom Tiffany does have a
legitimate chance to win,
even in this environment.
>> You know, when I look at
this big financial push for
conservatives here, I can't
help but think about the
2010 election cycle a
little bit, because I
remember that year, there
was a lot of talk in the
closing days of the
election that unions were
the big spenders in that
year's elections. They were
the big dogs in in that
year's fight. And we kind
of remember how that turned
out. It was pretty much the
worst year for Democrats
ever, basically, or at
least since we've been
covering politics. Zac, one
of the most consequential
wave elections that we have
covered. And so it doesn't
always work when you pour
money into a race. On the
other hand, David Crowley
is not a well-known
household name in Wisconsin.
And so when Tom Tiffany can
go out and kind of define
him, there's an argument to
be made that that money
gets more bang for the buck.
You've talked to both of
the candidates very
recently, David Crowley and
Tom Tiffany, and you get a
sense that an issue, gas
prices specifically could
become front and center in
this race for governor. How
are they talking about it
and why now?
>> Why now is because they
keep skyrocketing. Anyone
who has to regularly drive
anywhere knows that gas
prices are only going up.
It's becoming a bigger
issue with diesel,
specifically because that's
rising at an even faster
rate. So if you have a
diesel truck or you have
any connection to truckers
that need to bring supplies
to your business, or
farmers having to worry
about harvesting crops or
paying for fertilizer,
which also deals with
diesel and other fuel and
oil related subsidies.
There's all sorts of issues
that are really making this
the highest profile, but I
think the true answer to
that is you have to go
beyond maybe the people
that watch us program, and
it's the nonpolitically
invested people. When do
they tune into elections
when it affects them
personally and they can
feel it. I've spoken to so
many people, some in my own
family, who absolutely hate
politics. They don't want
anything to do with it.
They don't want to talk
about it. But when gas goes
up, when eggs go up, when
beef goes up, when they can
feel it and see it
everywhere, they say, why
is this happening? And who
can I blame? Which is why
in 2022, when we saw gas
prices surge, they blamed
Biden. Biden can have all
the answers in the world
about why it was
international. It wasn't
his fault. Same thing's
happening now. It's whoever
is in charge is going to
get blamed when prices
surge, no matter what the
nuance in an answer is. And
these these are voters that
don't look at political
nuance. They don't want to
spend 30 minutes hearing
about global supply chains
or foreign conflicts. They
want to know, why is it so
expensive for me to fill up
my truck.
>> And I mean, in this
particular election, we do
have I think Democrats have
a decent cause effect case
to be made here.
>> The straight line.
>> The president, Donald
Trump, decided to go to war
in Iran. And that has been
a huge factor affecting
fuel prices. Rich, one of
our candidates for governor
is in Congress. And this
has come up in Congress, of
course, with war powers,
resolutions, you name it.
How is Tom Tiffany voting
on those? And what's he
saying about it?
>> Well, he voted against
the the Democrats War
Powers Resolution. That
would have essentially
forced an end to the
conflict several times. So
there's that. But but now
he's essentially saying,
well, the governor,
Governor Evers, could do
something. Now, you know,
there's various things that
the governor could do to
ease taxes or etc. to bring
the price down a little bit.
So that is that's a bit of
a tightrope answer there,
where he doesn't want to
cross the president. But
also Tiffany did recently
say it's time to wrap up
the war. So there's that. I
also want to mention that
in the third Congressional
District race, which is my
home turf here. Derrick Van
Orden, a Republican
congressman, incumbent, he
was on Twitter and
essentially blaming oil
companies for price gouging.
And that I've seen from
some other Republicans who
you wouldn't expect that
sort of rhetoric focused on
industry or or, you know, a
big industry like oil and
gas. You wouldn't expect
that. So it was kind of
notable. And I felt I had
to mention.
>> It kind of normally the
proudly capitalist captains
of industry, but their
backs are against the wall
here in this moment in 2026.
So the candidates, Crowley
and Tiffany, have been
talking about other issues
with a pretty good link to
the national debate.
They've come out with their
own versions of this
anti-corruption agenda. I
think they framed it a
little bit differently, but
they both talked about
going to fight corruption.
Ana you covered the David
Crowley version of this.
What's he talking about?
>> Yeah, so he kind of came
out and he proposed four
things that he said would
be in his budget on day one.
And so that would include
banning state officeholders
from trading stocks from
participating in prediction
markets. There would be a
sort of imposed gap on when
energy regulators could go
to work for energy
companies two years, and
then also a change to kind
of public record laws. And
he framed this very much in
the context of Washington,
DC, and sort of saying that
there's all this corruption
going on in Washington. We
don't have the power to
address that. But what we
can do is kind of fight
stuff here. And so it was
an interesting way, I think,
of trying to frame things
against President Donald
Trump without necessarily
naming him with the kind of
understanding that Tom
Tiffany and President Trump
are pretty closely linked.
The other thing that was
kind of interesting is that
a couple of days later, Tom
Tiffany came out with his
own platform. And so it
also kind of shows this
dynamic right now in this
race where the candidates
really have to answer one
another. And so you see
kind of how close they are
and how close they
understand themselves to be,
because they can't kind of
dismiss when one person
comes out with a policy
proposal, the other person
needs to respond, right?
>> It was a data centers a
few weeks ago, and now
corruption and Rich, you
covered the Tom Tiffany
version of this up by Eau
Claire. What what is
anti-corruption mean to Tom
Tiffany? What's his
platform look like?
>> Well, he talked a lot
about the federal
investigations and findings
of, you know, Medicaid,
fraud, etc. from the in
Wisconsin and elsewhere,
there was talk about
Minnesota and the the fraud
that was announced by the
federal government in that
state. So that's the kind
of fraud he was talking
about. He said there's been
success at the federal
level. It's time to look in
Wisconsin. So Tiffany's
proposal is to essentially
do more audits of of every
state agency. And Wisconsin
already has a nonpartisan
legislative audit bureau.
And there is a committee in
the legislature that is run
by Republicans right now
that can tell it to do
additional audits on top of
like the annual audit of
state government. That is
done. And they have done
that, and they've even
audited some some groups
that have gotten some some
flak from Republicans or
some money that went to
these groups. Like there's
this new cap organization
in green Bay that had some
financial troubles and shut
down. So he mentioned those
audits and essentially that
his own office, the
Department of
Administration, if he were
elected governor, would be
going through agency
budgets as well as the
Audit Bureau. So that's a
little bit of a new thing.
And he also said we need
more transparency,
essentially online
dashboards, where you can
go and see where every
penny is spent, how it's
spent. And he referenced a
site that I didn't even
know existed, open Book
Wisconsin, which already
does this, but he said it
needs to be modernized and,
and just be smoother
because it's a bit of a
clunky website, but
interesting information on
there. So that's kind of
his pitch.
>> So David Crowley going
after Congress, where Tom
Tiffany serves Tom Tiffany
kind of attacking
Democratic Governor Tony
Evers, David Crowley's
endorser in chief, Zac, why
this message at this moment
in time in 2026?
>> I think what we're
seeing from each of these
candidates is they are
taking the issues that
voters say they care about,
like affordability, pricing,
and corruption, and
government transparency,
and they are kind of
gaslighting it right around
their own issues that have
been in their pet projects
forever. Because when
affordability, it's prices
and gouging. And when
Democrats and Republicans
talk about affordability,
it's your taxes. It's the
same issues they've been
doing all along. And this
corruption stuff. It's like
every single year we hear
Republicans talk about
fraud and social welfare
programs and more audits,
more audits. There have
been audits all along. As
Rich said, none of these
are new. They're not
unaudited programs, but it
kind of says to the voter,
oh, yeah, we hear what
you're complaining about,
and we're ready to do that.
And in fact, it's something
we've we've been talking
about all along. You should
vote for me because that's
what I want to do too. So
it's a way of taking these
fears that the voters are
really upset about and
saying, hey, you're already
ready to vote for me.
That's what I'm talking
about too. So rebranding,
relabeling these old
>> A new package, not
necessarily a new platform.
Before we wrap up here,
there was a primary on one
side for governor and
essentially not on the
other. You have been
covering a unity tour for
Democrats led by Francesca
Hong, who came up just
short in the primary. What
is she saying? And does the
Democratic Party need
unifying right now?
>> I mean, this is a really
kind of interesting moment.
So she's kind of hitting
the road to make the case
that Democrats have to get
this trifecta. They need
the legislature. They need
the governor's office.
Because I think there was
this question right after
the election. Would her
supporters kind of go away?
And again, with how tight
Wisconsin races are,
Democrats can't afford to
lose any of those voters.
And so this will be a
really interesting moment
to kind of see how gettable
or get backable her
supporters are for Crowley
because he'll need them to
win.
>> That's all the time we
have for today. This has
been inside Wisconsin
politics. Be sure to follow
us on PBS, wisconsin.org,
wpri.org, YouTube, or
wherever you get your
podcasts.